{"tossups": [{"question": "This battle was followed by a series of harsh winter rains that led the losing side to experience the infamous \u201cMud March.\u201d The winning side in this battle was able to set up defenses along Marye\u2019s Heights after the losing side experienced delays in setting pontoon bridges across the Rappahannock. Joseph Hooker was appointed commander of the Army of the Potomac shortly after this battle. For the point, name this December 1862 victory for Robert E. Lee over Ambrose Burnside in Virginia.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Fredericksburg</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man co-wrote a book in favor of gender equality with his wife Harriet Taylor called<em> The Subjection</em> <em>of Women</em> and was the first member of Parliament to call for women\u2019s suffrage. This philosopher argued for total liberty with the exception of infringing on others in his \u201charm principle,\u201d and he advocated the\u201cgreatest good for the greatest number.\u201d For the point, name this philosopher who, along with Jeremy Bentham, founded utilitarianism.", "answer": "John Stuart<b> Mill</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "During this period, a recent convert to Catholicism was publicly executed and fired out of a cannon in the general direction of Poland. During this period, the de la Gardie unit upheld the rule of Prince Shuisky before it was completely destroyed at the Battle of Klushino, which led to Gustavus Adolphus waging the Ingrian War. Men pretending to be the dead prince Dimitri arose during, for the point, what Russian period of upheaval that ended in 1613 with Michael Romanov taking the throne?", "answer": "<b> Time of Troubles</b> (or<b> Smutnoe vremya</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s losers were dubbed the \u201cConvention Army\u201d after a treaty allowing them to return home was broken. The Treaty of Alliance was confirmed as a result of this battle. The sniper Timothy Murphy legendarily shot a general during fighting for Bemis Heights during this battle. Benedict Arnold was incensed that Horatio Gates received credit for the surrender of John Burgoyne in, for the point, what decisive 1777 victory for the colonists in New York?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Saratoga</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader created the Economic Policy Board in an attempt to revive the economy, but was instead mocked for giving out buttons that read \u201cWhip Inflation Now\u201d to supporters. This President, who pledged not to intervene with the Indonesian invasion of East Timor, lost support for declaring that \u201cour long national nightmare is over\u201d as he pardoned his predecessor. For the point, name this president who was soundly defeated by Jimmy Carter in 1976 after replacing Richard Nixon.", "answer": "Gerald<b> Ford</b> (or Leslie<b> King</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A general died in a plane crash during this war after exceeding his plane\u2019s weight limit by packing too many dress uniforms. The \u201cValley of the Fallen\u201d memorial was created to honor the dead of this war, whose winner may have killed generals Jose Sanjurjo and Emilio Mola after serving in the Rif War. For the point, name this war in which Nationalists led by Francisco Franco took cities such as Seville and Barcelona.", "answer": "<b> Spanish Civil</b> War (accept<b> Guerra Civil Espanola</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Warren Jeffs, the leader of a \u201cFundamentalist\u201d offshoot of this religion, was on the FBI Most Wanted list until his arrest in 2011. This religion, which teaches that spouses live together in the afterlife after Celestial Marriage, notes that Adam lived at a location near Jameson, Missouri after expulsion from the Garden. For the point, name this religion whose scriptures were legendarily translated from golden plates by Joseph Smith.", "answer": "The Church of Jesus Christ of<b> Latter-Day Saints</b> (or<b> LDS</b> Church; accept the<b> Mormon</b>s; accept<b> Mormon</b>ism)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This ruler fought the battles of Chanderi and Khanwa to consolidate his rule against Rana Sanga. This ruler\u2019s early career was marked by constant wars with Mohammed Shaybani over Kabul and Ferghana. The governor of Lahore, Daulat Khan, invited this man to launch an invasion force against Ibrahim Lodi. This man was subsequently victorious at the Battle of Panipat. For the point, name the founder of the Mughal Empire.", "answer": "<b> Babur</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man motivated his soldiers by telling them, \u201cI do not order you to fight, I order you to die\u201dduring a defense of his homeland. Anger over the Treaty of Sevres prompted this man to lead a war of independence, leading his country to be recognized in the Treaty of Lausanne. He later implemented\u201creformism\u201d as part of the Six Arrows ideology, which banned the fez in an attempt at westernization. For the point, name this founder of modern Turkey.", "answer": "Mustafa<b> Kemal Ataturk</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "On this island, Edmund Halley tracked the movement of 341 stars and Nevil Maskelyne and Robert Waddington tried to observe the transit of Venus. Sayyid bin Barghash, the Sultan of Zanzibar, was exiled to this island, as was the son of Cetshwayo. On this island, Sir Hudson Lowe served as a jailer for another famous prisoner, who had previously escaped from Elba to lead the Hundred Days restoration in France. For the point, name this island that served as the final prison for Napoleon.", "answer": "<b> St. Helena</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "William Alden Smith led an inquest into the causes of this event, in which reporters incorrectly noted that its victims had been saved by the<em> Virginian</em>. Benjamin Guggenheim, John Jacob Astor, and captain Edward Smith were killed during this event, which occurred during a journey between Southampton and New York City. The White Star Line\u2019s claims were proven false in, for the point, what 1912 disaster that killed more than 1,500 people in the cold North Atlantic ocean?", "answer": "sinking of the RMS<b> Titanic</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Clarence Borel died before his lawsuit against manufacturers of this product reached its conclusion in his favor in 1973. The chrysotile form of this substance was once used as costuming and props in films, such as the snow in<em> The Wizard of Oz</em>. In 2018, Johnson & Johnson was ordered to pay over $4 billion in damages related to this material\u2019s use in its talcum powder. Mesothelioma is a cancer most commonly caused by exposure to, for the point, what mineral that was once very commonly used in fireproof insulation?", "answer": "<b> asbestos</b> (accept descriptions of<b> asbestos</b>-based insulation; prompt on insulation before mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Prior to this battle, Anne Savary was sent to Olmutz to ask for a ceasefire. The winning general declared, \u201cnever interrupt your enemy when he is making a mistake\u201d during this battle, where a heavy fog helped obscure Nicholas Soult\u2019s attack up the Pratzen Heights. This battle led to the Treaty of Pressburg and the creation of the Confederation of the Rhine. For the point, name this 1805 battle in which France decisively defeated the Russian and Austrian armies.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Austerlitz</b> (or the Battle of the<b> Three Emperors</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler may have ordered the death of Augusto Vandor, one of the leaders within the CGT union that this man opposed. This man was supported by the Triple A death group and targeted the left wing Montoneros during a massacre at Ezeiza airport. The descamisados, or shirtless ones, backed this man, who was succeeded by his third wife, Isabel. For the point, name this three time President of Argentina who benefited from his marriage to the popular Evita.", "answer": "Juan<b> Peron</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event\u2019s survivors were rounded up in the Drexel Mission Fight a day later. James Forsyth\u2019s men perpetrated this event, which was stoked by fears that Wovoka\u2019s \u201cghost dance\u201d movement meant imminent attack. This event began when the deaf man Black Coyote refused to hand over his rifle, leading army troops to fire upon the Pine Ridge reservation. For the point, name this 1890 event in which members of the Lakota were massacred in South Dakota.", "answer": "<b> Wounded Knee</b> massacre", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Senator Jesse Thomas proposed that the southern border of this state be extended across the rest of the Louisiana Purchase as a line for slavery\u2019s expansion. After Congressman James Tallmadge added an amendment to this state\u2019s request to join the Union, it floundered in the Senate. This state ultimately joined the Union along with a free state that had been part of Massachusetts, Maine. For the point, name this state that became a slave state as part of a namesake compromise in 1820.", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "News of this event broke after Shaul Ladany jumped off a roof to escape. This event led to the death of Ahmed Bouchiki during a case of mistaken identity in Lillehammer. Operation Wrath of God sought to track down the perpetrators of this event. Led by Lutiff Atif, the planners of this event demanded that leaders of the Red Army Faction be released. Members of Black September committed, for the point, what 1972 crisis in which 11 Israeli athletes were murdered?", "answer": "<b> Munich</b> Massacre (accept descriptive answers relating to the Israeli hostage crisis at the 1972 <b>Munich</b> Summer Olympics; prompt on partial answers that don\u2019t name the city)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This event was supported by the Six Society of intellectuals, who wished to promote \u201ccivilization and enlightenment.\u201d Supporters of this event used the slogan \u201cenrich the country, strengthen the military,\u201dand its detractors launched the Satsuma Revolt to slow its reforms. The Charter Oath provided legal backing for this event, which sought to promote Western ideals and end feudalism. For the point, name this 1868 event that restored power to the Japanese emperor.", "answer": "<b> Meiji</b> Restoration", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This monarch may have prompted Robert Dudley to push Amy Robsart down a flight of stairs. The Babington and Ridolfi plots sought to assassinate this ruler but were thwarted by the advisor Francis Walsingham. This ruler rallied the troops at Tilbury, where she declared she had the \u201cheart and stomach of a king\u201d in opposition to an invasion of the Spanish Armada. For the point, name this daughter of Henry VIII, a \u201cVirgin Queen\u201d of England.", "answer": "<b> Elizabeth I</b> (prompt on Elizabeth)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This period featured the widespread usage of the phrase \u201cthe people want to bring down the regime\u201din graffiti and chants. The \u201cRevolution of Dignity\u201d took place against Ali Saleh during this period. After his vegetable cart had been seized by government officials, Mohamed Bouazizi set himself on fire; that incident sparked this period, which led to the downfall of the Gaddafi and Mubarak governments. For the point, name this 2010 period in which uprisings commenced across the Middle East.", "answer": "<b> Arab Spring</b> (prompt on descriptions of revolutions in Tunisia, Yemen, Libya, and/or Egypt)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle turned when the Ne\u2019arin detachment suddenly arrived from Amurru. Prior to this battle, one side was tricked into thinking that the enemy was at Aleppo by two Shashu spies. After he was forced back towards the Orontes River, Muwatalli II was defeated in this battle and subsequently signed the world\u2019s first peace treaty. For the point, name this largest chariot battle in history, a 1274 BC battle where Ramesses II fought the Hittites.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Kadesh</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Membership in this group swelled after the Knights of Mary Phagan formed to murder Leo Frank. Four years after it was formed at the Maxwell House Hotel, the Force Act was passed to curb this group\u2019s activities. Founded by Nathan Bedford Forrest, this group experienced a revival after it was glorified in D.W. Griffith\u2019s film<em> The Birth of a Nation</em>. For the point, name this American white supremacist group.", "answer": "<b> K</b>u<b> K</b>lux<b> K</b>lan (prompt on \u201cthe Klan\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The life of a miller in this modern-day country is depicted in Carlo Ginzburg\u2019s<em> The Cheese and the</em> <em>Worms</em>. Holy Roman Emperor Charles V\u2019s attempt to invade this country was defeated by the Lombard League, and Francis I was captured at the Battle of Pavia in this country. A city in this country was ruled by the Guelphs when it faced the Ciompi revolt of wool workers; that city was later ruled by Cosimo and Lorenzo the Magnificent. For the point, name this country where the Medici family dominated the politics of Florence.", "answer": "<b> Italy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Although it\u2019s not Italian, this legislation was passed with the support of the Squadrone Volante [squad-roh-nay voh-lan-tay]. One country entered into this legislation in part due to crippling financial losses in the Darien Scheme. These acts forced one country to acknowledge succession laws established in the earlier Act of Settlement. For the point, name this set of acts, passed in 1706 and 1707, that merged Scotland and England into Great Britain.", "answer": "1706/7 Act(s) of<b> Union</b> (until \u201cmerged\u201d is read, accept descriptions of the<b> creation of Great Britain</b>, or the<b> union</b> (or<b> merger</b>, etc.) of<b> Scotland and England</b>, or similar; after\u201cmerged\u201d is read, you can still accept descriptions, but they must say the word<b> union</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}